Finding aid for the Xavier University Campus Buildings and Properties collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
- Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 2, 1993; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Legdewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 2, Supplement 1, 1986; 1993; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 9, Folder 2)
  This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Two's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.
- Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 2, Supplement 2, 1993; undated; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 2, Supplement 3, 1993; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 3, 1993-1997; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Legdewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 3, Supplement 1 Herald Avenue Program, 1958; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 10, Folder 2)
  This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Three's large three-ring binder. The materials are apparently photocopies of information on the closing of Herald Avenue. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.
- Proposed Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Book 3, Supplement 2, 1987; 1993; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 10, Folder 3)
  This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Three's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.
  This folder may contain material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.
- Proposed Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Book 3, Supplement3, 1993; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Ledgewood Lawsuit, 1993-1994; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 11, Folder 1)
  This folder contains documentation on a lawsuit concerning Ledgewood Avenue. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.
- Lindner Family Physics Hall, 1991 October 30 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  This folder contains brochures from the dedication of the building on October 30, 1991.
  The Lindner Physics Hall is located on the west side of the Academic Mall between Logan Hall and the Gallagher Student Center. It was named in honor the family of Carl H. Lindner, the principal donor. Mr. Lindner was a noted Cincinnati businessman and philanthropist. The hall was dedicated on October 30, 1991. The hall houses the "Foucault Pendulum" and the Xavier Observatory.
- Logan Hall, 1929-1953; undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  This folder contains: 1. Last Will and Testament of Mr. Thomas J. Logan along with correspondence pertaining to it; 2. Agenda of the Logan Hall Planning Committee.
  Logan Hall is located on the Academic Mall between Albers Biology Hall and the Lindner Family Physics Hall. It was named in honor of Thomas J. Logan, the principal donor. It was built at an original cost of $ 651,000.00. It opened for classes in September, 1953 and was officially dedicated on May 22,1954.
  On June 4, 1952, the Century Depository Site, located on the plaza in front of the building, was dedicated by Thomas E. Murray, a member of the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission. At the dedication of the building in 1954, a "Century Depository" containing materials of a scientific nature was sealed. An atomic clock will open the depository on May 22, 2053.
- Logan Hall, 1950-1954 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  This folder contains correspondence pertaining to the construction of Logan Hall.
- Logan Hall, 1951-1953 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  This folder has correspondence containing the bids from contractors for the construction of Logan Hall.
- Logan Hall, 1946-1954 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  This folder contains: 1. Contracts for the construction of Logan Hall; 2. Requisitions for the payment of construction work on Logan Hall.
- Logan Hall, 1953-1958; undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  This folder contains: 1. Correspondence pertaining to the "Century Depository" located on the plaza outside the entrance to Logan Hall on the University Drive; 2. Correspondence pertaining to the Albert D. Cash Room on the first floor of Logan Hall; 3. Printed announcements about Logan Hall; 4. Drawings, pictures and photos of Logan Hall.
- Marion Hall and Carriage House, 1964-1976; undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  This folder contains a history of Marion Hall, some correspondence, photos, and sketches.
  Marion Hall with its Carriage House was located at 992 Marion Avenue. It was built around 1890 by a German carriage maker named Enger. In March, 1943, the Jesuit Community moved out of Hinkle Hall to make room for the 30th College Training Detachment of the U.S. Army Air Corps. Many of the Jesuits moved into Marion Hall where they lived until September, 1944, when the Air Corps program ended and the Jesuits moved back to Hinkle. On October 12, 1943, Xavier purchased Marion Hall while the Jesuits were living there. Marion became a dormitory in 1945. It housed about 60 students. It became an honors (HAB) dormitory in 1958. The Carriage House was located on the grounds of Marion Hall. It was a two-story structure located to the rear left of the mansion. At the end of the 1990-91 academic year, Marion was closed as a residence hall and the university sold the property shortly thereafter.
- McGrath Health and Wellness Center, 1956-2011 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  This folder contains information on the University Health Service and limited correspondence and other materials related to the service itself.
  The University Health Center has had different locations on campus since its inception in 1947. Originally it was found on the ground floor of the Schmidt Memorial Fieldhouse. Subsequently it moved to the Union House. In 1959 it moved to Sycamore House. In 1960 the facility was housed in McGrath Hall, in memory of the late Dr. Edward J. McGrath, a member of the university medical staff. In 1965 the Health Service moved to Ledgewood Avenue and shortly thereafter moved to the first floor of Kuhlman Hall. Lastly, the Health Center moved to the present location on Cleaney Avenue.
- O'Connor Sports Center, 1973-1977 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  This folder contains: 1. Preliminary plans for the Center; 2. Correspondence concerning construction of the Center, 1974-75; 3. Proposals (bids) from architectural firms, 1974.
  The O'Connor Sports Center is located on the west side of the campus near the soccer field and the Schmidt Memorial Fieldhouse. It was named in honor of Paul L. O'Connor, S.J., president of Xavier from 1955 to 1972. The groundbreaking ceremony for the first phase, named "The Ralph and Patricia Corbett Physical Education Building in the O'Connor Sports Center," took place on May 15, 1975. Dedication of the first phase took place on September 29, 1976. Dedication of the second phase took place on April 30, 1977.
- O'Connor Sports Center, 1975-1991 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  This folder contains: 1. Brochure about the Center; 2. Groundbreaking ceremonies for Phase One, the Ralph and Patricia Corbett Physical Education Building (May 15, 1975); 3. Dedication of Phase One, the Ralph and Patricia Corbett Physical Education Building (September 29, 1976); 4. Dedication of Phase Two (April 30, 1977); 5. Brochures and announcements about the Center's activities (1979-1990); 6. Photos and architect's drawing of the Center.
- Parking Garage (Proposed), 1965-1976 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  This folder contains limited correspondence and publications related to the question of parking.
  In the 1960s and 1970s there was some discussion of constructing a parking garage on the Xavier campus. None of these proposals were ever acted upon.
- Saint Barbara Hall, 2008 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  This folder contains limited historical information on St. Barbara Hall.
  Saint Barbara Hall is located at 3904 Winding Way on the west side of the campus. It was purchased by Xavier from the Melcher family in August, 1947. It has been used as the office of the Reserve Officers' Training Corps. (ROTC). St Barbara is the patron saint of armorers, artillerymen and military engineers.
- Schmidt Fieldhouse, 1950; 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  This folder contains correspondence, notes, sketches and other materials.
  Schmidt Memorial Fieldhouse was erected to the memory of Frederick A. Schmidt and Apolline Tetedoux Schmidt by their son, Walter S. Schmidt, Class of 1905. It was dedicated on March 7, 1928 The original cost of the structure was $ 325,000.00. In 1928, it was the largest college fieldhouse in Ohio.
- Schmidt Hall, 1966; 2013 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  This folder contains limited correspondence.
  Schmidt Hall (the Walter Seton Schmidt Library Building) is located between Edgecliff Hall (previously, the Alumni Science Hall) and Hinkle Hall. It was named in honor of Walter Seton Schmidt, Class of 1905, who was the principal donor. The original cost of the structure was $ 260,000.00. It was dedicated in May, 1926. The building originally housed the University Library including the high vaulted Mary G. Lodge Reading Room. It also housed Bellarmine Chapel, classrooms and the seismographic station. Later it housed the University Comptroller's office, the Conaton Board Room, the offices of the university president, the academic vice president (provost) and the financial vice president.
- Schott Hall, 1962-1970; 1983 May 10 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. Program of the Dedication Ceremony (June 27, 1970); 2. Correspondence pertaining to the construction of Schott Hall.
  The Walter E. Schott, Sr., Memorial Building was named in honor of Walter E. Schott, Sr.. The principal donor was the Walter E. Schott Family Foundation. Built as the residence for the Xavier Jesuit Community at a cost of $ 2,200,000.00, the facility was dedicated and blessed on June 27, 1970, by Paul E. Leibold, Archbishop of Cincinnati. In early January, 1991, the Jesuit Community moved out of Schott Hall into the Linkshire Apartment building at 3844 Victory Parkway. Schott then became a faculty office building. Several years later, the Financial Aid Office and the Undergraduate Admission Office moved into the lower floors of the Hall.
- Schott Hall, 1969-1971; undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  This folder contains photos, plans and sketches of the Hall.
- Smith Hall, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  This folder contains a brochure concerning Smith Hall.
  See XUA-53, the Xavier University Master Building Plans collection for further information on Smith Hall.
  Smith Hall was named in honor of Stephen and Dolores Smith. Stephen Smith is a member of the Xavier Class of 1968 and is a member of the Xavier Board of Trustees. This facility is home to Xavier's Williams College of Business Administration. It was dedicated in July, 2010 and opened in August, 2010. It is part of the James E. Hoff, S.J., Academic Quadrangle. With its signature two story atrium, scrolling stock tickers, high-tech classrooms, Wall Street-style trading room and Bloomberg financial database terminals, Smith Hall is state-of-the-art.
- Sycamore House, 1949-1954; 1974 October 3 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  Built around 1911, Sycamore House was purchased by Xavier University on May 17, 1954. At one time this was the home of Fritz Reiner, the conductor of the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra. Originally named "the Elet Hall Annex," it served as a student residence adjoining Elet Hall. It later served as the office of the University Health Center. Currently it serves as the office of Psychological Services.
- Tibbles Avenue, Closing of, 1964-1965; undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  Sometime in late 1964 or early 1965 the City of Cincinnati vacated Tibbles Avenue between Herald Avenue and Riley Avenue and sold the property to Xavier University. Tibbles Avenue was apparently located just east of where Husman Hall and Kuhlman Hall now stand.
- Union House (Red Building), 1942-1946; 1966; undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  This folder includes articles and correspondence about this facility.
  Union House was located on Dana Avenue near Winding Way. This structure was built as the clubhouse of the Avondale Athletic Club around 1898 and was a landmark in the area. Also known as the "Old Red Building," it served as the university cafeteria and recreation center until the University Center was built in 1965. It was razed in 1966 to make way for the Joseph Building.
- University Center Building, 1958-2000 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. Groundbreaking Ceremony (December 12, 1963); 2. Dedication of the Center (October 31, 1965); 3. The Theatre in the University Center; 4. The Musketeer Grill and its mural in the University Center; 5. Food Service in the University Center; 6. Proposal for a rathskeller (bar) in the Center (1973); 7. Relocation of Tucker's Tavern (1976).
  The University Center Building was located where the Gallagher Student Center now stands. It was built at an original cost of $ 2,250,000.00. Groundbreaking took place on December 12, 1963. The dedication and blessing by Archbishop Alter took place on October 31, 1965. This building contained a cafeteria, theatre, the Musketeer Grill, a bookstore, lounges, a game room, and offices, including that of the university's president. It was razed in the summer of 2000 in order to make room for the Gallagher Student Center.
- University Center, 1957-1967; undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  This folder contains: 1. Early proposals pertaining to the Center; 2. Papers pertaining to the Federal loan to finance the Center; 3. Brochure about the Center.
- University Center, 1965; undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  This folder includes floor plans, sketches and photos of the Center.
- University Center, 1964-1966 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  This folder contains correspondence and records pertaining to the construction and use of the Center, including the minutes of the Committee on Policy for the University Center Building.
- Victory Parkway Fields, 1998-2002 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  This folder includes memorandums, news clippings and diagrams, a draft lease agreement, along with other materials.
  Victory Parkway Fields are located on Victory Parkway between Ledgewood and Hopkins Avenues in North Avondale. These grounds were dedicated and opened on June 16, 2001. Under an agreement signed by Xavier University and the Cincinnati Park Board and unanimously approved by Cincinnati City Council, the city leased this land to Xavier for $1.00 per year for 98 years. Xavier provided the entire cost of the $ 2,000,000.00 renovation and will maintain the land at no cost to taxpayers. The fields include a soccer field, a baseball diamond, 6 tennis courts and a bike/walking path.
- The Villa (Theda Bara House), 2011; undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  This folder contains limited correspondence and a news clipping.
  The Villa was also called the Theda Bara House and also the Honors House. Xavier acquired the Villa in 1979 from Dr. Joseph Link, professor emeritus of economics, as part of a six-buildings deal which included three apartments (the Linkshire, the University and the Manor House), the Tudor Lodge, the Fraternity House, and the Villa. The Villa was razed in the 2000s. For a history of the Villa and its historical significance, consult the Xavier Magazine, Fall 2001 issue, in which the article entitled "This Old House" appears.
- Village Student Apartment Complex, 1986-1987 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. A proposal from Lorenz and Williams, Incorporated; 2. Phase One Report; 3. Schematic Site Design for Phase One Report.
  The Xavier Village Student Apartment Complex is located on the southeast corner of Dana Avenue and Victory Parkway. The groundbreaking ceremony was on September 28, 1988. The dedication ceremony was on September 29, 1989. It opened in the fall of 1989.It comprised 56 apartments of either 2 or 3 or 4 bedrooms each.
- Village Student Apartment Complex, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  This folder contains: 1. Market Survey and Analysis (1987); 2. Design, Development Agreement; Financial Scenarios; 3. Schematic Design of Project; 4. Correspondence.
- Village Student Apartment Complex, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  This folder contains: 1. Planning and construction of the Village (1998); 2. Deed of purchase of the land for the Village (1988).
- Village Student Apartment Complex, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  This folder contains: 1. Final Focus Group Report (1988); 2. The minutes and final report of the committee charged with preparing a marketing plan for the Village.
- Village Student Apartment Complex, 1988-1991 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  This folder contains: 1. Groundbreaking ceremony (September 28, 1988); 2. Brochure announcing the opening of the Village; 3. Dedication Ceremony (September 29, 1989); 4. Correspondence, announcements, etc. (1989-1991).
- Walker House, 1969; undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  The Walker House was located at 1500 Dana Avenue on the north side of the street. Xavier University purchased this residential home. On November 23, 1969, the house was dedicated to the memory of Dr. Russell J. Walker, a professor of accounting and former assistant dean of the College of Business Administration. At the time of the dedication the house served as the office of the Institute of Business Services and the Hospital Administration program. Later it was the Financial Aid office. It was razed sometime in the 1990s to make way for the Admission Office parking lot on Dana Avenue outside Schott Hall.
- Xavier Commons (Student Residence), 2000-2001 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  This folder includes a news release, news clippings and a diagram.
  The Xavier Commons is located on Herald Avenue opposite the Cintas Center. It's original cost was $ 14,000,000.00. It opened in the fall of 2001. It has 71 apartments including one for the president of the University. It is a four story building. About 250 of the approximately 274 residents live in 4 bedroom units. The remainder are in 2 and 3 bedroom apartments. Construction was funded through 30 year tax-exempt bonds issued by the Ohio Higher Education Facilities Commission.
- Building Inventories, 2000-2006; undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  This folder contains various inventories of Xavier buildings. Inventories give such information as date of construction, square footage, street addresses, etc..
- Property Transactions, 1931-1968; undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  This folder contains limited correspondence concerning various Xavier property transactions.
- Donors, Supervisors, Etc., 1954-1972; undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  This folder contains: 1. List of donors of buildings (1954); 2. Dedication Committees (1965); 3. Lists of building supervisors (1972); 4. Memorials on campus (undated).